Campus Construction; Collection ua950.005
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Campus Construction Collection
1951-1987
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua950.005
1.5 cubic ft.
This collection contains planning documents used in the development and construction of the University at Albany, SUNY's Uptown campus.
Administrative History
The University's main campus, the Uptown Campus, has been described as a distinctive work of modern art. Designed in 1961-1962 by renowned American architect Edward Durell Stone (1902-1978), the campus bears Stone's signature style of bold unified design, evident in buildings from the U.S. Embassy in New Delhi to the Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in Washington, D.C. Construction on the initial set of buildings began in 1962 and finished in 1971. The next building to be built on campus, Freedom Quad, opened in 1988.
The Uptown Campus is defined by a central Academic Podium complex, main fountain complex with carillon tower, and four quadrangle residence halls that dominate much of the campus.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains planning documents used in the development and construction of the University at Albany, SUNY's Uptown campus. Of particular interest are the regular progress memos providing indepth information about challenges and development with construction.
The majority of plans included in this collection (such as the 1974 plans, 30,000-40,000 student scenario) were never realized and the buildings were not constructed in the 1970s as anticipated in the previous decade.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has two series: Planning Documents and Subject Files. Both are arranged alphabetically.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Architecture; Campus planning -- New York (State); College facilities -- New York (State) -- Planning; Correspondence; Clippings; UAlbany Reference Collections; State University of New York at Albany; New York State University Construction Fund
- Photographs, 1964-1973; 257 items
  Biographical / Historical
  The new SUNY Albany campus was contructed on the west side of the City of Albany on the site of the former Albany Country Club. Designed by architect Edward Durell Stone, the campus is a preeminent example of postmodernist architecture. The academic podium at the center is one of the largest poured-in-place concrete structures in the world.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains photographs taken during the construction of UAlbany's Uptown Campus. The images were taken by photographer E.M. Weil, under contract with either SUNY Albany or the SUNY Construction Fund.
  - Construction of the University at Albany's main campus. Aerial photograph from the southwest., ca. 1965
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Chemistry building showing the front panels, facing North-West., 1965 January 11
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The area between the Business Adminstration and the Library buildings, facing North-East., 1967 January 16
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus.The Infirmary building looking West., 1966 January 20
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking Easterly., 1966 January 20
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The North end of the second floor of the Infirmary building, facing West., 1966 January 20
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking South., 1966 January 20
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The North-East corner of the Biology building site on the left, facing West., 1964 January 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Business Adminisitration and the Administration buildings from the West., 1966 January 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Fine Arts building from the West with the Earth Sciences building in the rear., 1966 January 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology, Chemistry, and Phyisics buildings from the South-East., 1965 October 11
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Chemistry and physics buildings from the Earth Sciences building., 1965 October 12
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Room 338 of the Biology building, facing the North-West., 1965 October 12
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking North., 1965 October 18
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking West., 1965 October 18
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking East., 1965 October 18
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking South., 1965 October 18
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. From the viewpoint of the Physics building's roof, a close up of the Fine Arts building., 1965 October 26
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Adminstration building, with the Fine Arts building to the right, looking East., 1965 October 26
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The second floor of the Biology building showing the barrel vaults on the floor and ceiling., 1964 October 9
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building roof showing drainage through, facing North., 1964 October 9
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building and podium looking South-West., 1964 November 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Chemistry and Biology buildings looking North-West from the podium., 1964 November 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the Northside of the dam looking South., 1963 November 14
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the Northside of the dam looking South., 1963 November 14
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the Northside of the dam looking South., 1963 November 14
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking North., 1965 November 18
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking East., 1965 November 18
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking South-West., 1965 November 18
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Infirmary building looking West., 1965 November 18
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the Northside of the dam looking South., 1963 November 4
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the Northside of the dam looking South., 1963 November 4
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Room 338 of the Biology building featuring the cabinets., 1965 November 8
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The interior of room 328 of the Chemistry building, facing East., 1965 December 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake looking South., 1963 December 16
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake looking South., 1963 December 16
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake looking Southwest., 1963 December 16
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus, part 2. Facing east from northeast corner roof of Social Sciences Building., 1965 December 21
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Greenhouse looking East from the Biology podium., 1966 December 22
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The interior of the Greenhouse facing West., 1966 December 22
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Business Administration building, looking South-East showing the overhang., 1966 December 5
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The interior of the Fine Arts gallery facing South-East., 1966 December 5
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Sciences and Fine Arts buildings from the Physics Podium, December 21, 1965. [2624]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Science building from Biology building, December 21, 1965 [2625]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Sciences building looking Northwest from the roof of the Biology building, October 26, 1965. [2844]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, showing the second floor columns of the Earth Sciences building facing the Southwest, June 23, 1965. [2870]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, Earth Sciences building showing first floor facing West, May 24, 1965. [2890]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Sciences and Fine Arts buildings from the roof of the Biology building, September 22, 1965. [2894]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Sciences Building from the Southeast corner, September 22, 1965. [2895]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Sciences and Fine Arts buildings from the Northeast, November 24, 1965. [2909]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, Education and Humanities facing the Northwest from the student/faculty podium, February 11, 1965. [10089]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, court between Biology and Earth Sciences buildings looking Southwest, May 25, 1966 [2654]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Fine Arts and Earth Sciences buildings looking Southeast, May 25, 1966. [2673]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Science building facing Northwest, January 24, 1966. [2735]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Sciences and Fine Arts buildings facing the Northwest from the Biology Podium, February 22, 1966. [2786]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Northeast Court and Earth Sciences Building from the Northeast, April 26, 1966. [2861]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Sciences and Fine Arts buildings taken from the roof of the Biology building, April 26, 1966. [16052]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Room #236 of the Earth Sciences building facing North, March 24, 1967. [2713]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, area between Earth Sciences and Fine Arts buildings from the Theater Podium, January 16, 1967. [2748]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings, part II, Earth Sciences building first floor center hall looking East, June 27, 1967. [2849]
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The first floor of the Biology building interior of the South-West corner of the room, facing West., 1965 February 11
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Fine Arts gallery facing South., 1967 February 15
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Looking South into the court between the Fine Arts and Earth Sciences buildings., 1967 February 15
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The North-west court between the Business Adminstration and Social Sciences buildings looking South., 1967 February 15
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Business Administration and Admistration buildings from the Library roof., 1966 February 22
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Chemistry building monitor roof facing the East., 1965 March 15
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building showing the construction of the roof overhang, facing South-West., 1965 March 15
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Humanities building facing South-West from the topside of the Library building., 1965 March 15
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Humanities and Education buildings from the top of the Student Faculty building, facing North-West., 1965 March 15
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus, part 1. Student-Faculty building, Northside, showing reflecting pool forms., 1966 March 17
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The South-East corner of the Chemistry building, looking North-West., 1964 March 20
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building, footings and the East wall looking South-West., 1964 March 20
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building footings and East wall, looking North-West., 1964 March 20
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Fine Arts building's roof facing West., 1966 March 21
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Adminsitration building looking North-East from the Library roof., 1966 March 21
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Business Adminstration building, looking East from the Social Sciences roof., 1966 March 21
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Looking South into the court between the Fine Arts and Earth Sciences buildings., 1967 March 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Room 353 of the Biology building facing East., 1966 March 8
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Room 253 of the Biology building facing West., 1966 March 8
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building site looking West from the East-side., 1964 April 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building site looking North-West from the Southeastern corner., 1964 April 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Chemistry building site looking North-West from the Southestern corner., 1964 April 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building site, facing the North showing the pipes and risers., 1964 April 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus, part 1. Fountain and court of the Student-Faculty building from the North., 1966 April 11
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The third floor Southwestern corner room of the Chemistry building., 1966 April 11
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus, part 2. Center court in the Lecture Halls, facing Southeast., 1969 April 21
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the North-side of the dam looking South., 1964 April 23
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the North-side of the dam looking South., 1964 April 23
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the North-side of the Dam looking South., 1964 April 23
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake from the North-South of the Dam looking South., 1964 April 23
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Looking South-East across the roof of the Business Adminstration and Administration buildings., 1967 April 25
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The court between the Fine Arts and Earth Sciences buildings, looking South., 1967 April 25
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The construction of the wall of the North podium and Business Adminstration building, looking East., 1967 April 25
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The interior of the Fine Arts building, facing East., 1966 April 26
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Business Administration and Adminstration buildings from the Social Sciences roof., 1966 April 26
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The top of the Humanities building with the Education building to the East., 1965 April 9
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The interior of the Chemistry building including the second floor and the framing for partitions., 1965 April 9
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology buildings facing North-East, showing the construction of the overhang., 1965 April 9
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building facing the South-east showing the overhang., 1965 April 9
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building's second floor washroom, showing the tiles., 1965 May 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building facing North, showing the overhang on the East-side and the Southeastern corner., 1965 May 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Humanities building and start of the podium South of the Library, looking South-West from the Library., 1965 May 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. A plastered room on the second floor of the Biology building featuring a light fixture on the right., 1965 May 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Chemistry building looking North, showing the start of the overhang on the South-side., 1965 May 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The paving on the podium, the East-side of the Biology building facing the North., 1966 May 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Greenhouse looking West from the Biology podium., 1966 May 10
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus, part 1. Fountain and court Northside of Student-Faculty Building, facing South., 1966 May 11
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The third floor of the Humanities building, facing East showing the corridor and wells., 1966 May 11
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus, part 1. Court between University Library and Administration Building., 1966 May 11
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The landscaping between the Administration building and Dorm number 3, facing the East., 1968 May 21
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The stairwell and court between the Biology and Earth Sciences buildings, facing North., 1967 May 23
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The stairwell and court between the Biology and Earth Sciences buildings, facing North., 1967 May 23
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Adminstration and Business building foundations looking West., 1965 May 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. Foundations of the Adminisration and Fine Arts buildings facing North-East., 1965 May 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Adminsitration building from the Library roof., 1966 May 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Administration buildings, looking East from the Social Sciences roof., 1966 May 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Administration building looking East from the Social Sciences roof., 1966 May 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Administration building from the Library roof., 1966 May 24
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Fine Arts and Earth Sciences buildings looking South-East., 1966 May 25
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The court between the biology and earth sciences building, looking South-west., 1966 May 25
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Chemistry and Biology buildings looking from the South-East to the North-West., 1964 May 6
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Biology building looking East to the West., 1964 May 6
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Humanities building site looking from South to North with the Social Sciences building to the left and the Library at the right., 1964 May 6
  - Construction of the University at Albany's academic buildings on the uptown campus. The Campus lake looking Westerly from the East side of the lake., 1964 June 10